A Guide to the Executive Papers of Governor James Hoge Tyler, 1860-1901 (bulk 1898-1901)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Executive Papers of Governor James Hoge Tyler, 1860-1901 (bulk 1898-1901)
The Library of Virginia
23349, 33675
0.45 cu. ft. (1 box)
Virginia Governor (1898-1902: Tyler)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Aquired from the Governor's Office 26 January 1947 and Novemember 1989.
Biographical Information
Governor James Hoge Tyler was the son of George and Eliza (Hoge) Tyler and was born in Caroline County on 11 August 1846. Hoge studied at Edge Hill Academy and at Minor's Academy with the intent of enrolling at the University of Virginia. In 1863, however, he left school and joined the Confederate Army. He served as a private until the end of the war in 1865, fighting mainly in Southwest Virginia. After the war, Hoge returned to his home in Pulaski County to begin life as a farmer.
Tyler's interest in politics began in the early 1870's when he was elected President of the Pulaski Farmers' Club. In the spring of 1873, he ran for the 39th senatorial seat of Virginia which included the counties of Pulaski, Giles, Bland and Tazewell. In September, however, he withdrew his name from contention after facing overwhelming opposition. Tyler would again run for political office in 1877 and was elected in November as a Democratic conservative to the Virginia Senate. In 1889, he ran for Governor of Virginia but failed to receive the Democratic nomination. As a consolation, he was placed on the ballot as lieutenant governor and served in that position from 1890 to 1894. Finally, in 1897, he was elected Virginia's 43rd Governor.
Tyler took office 1 January 1898. His four years in office were focused on creating a honest and efficient government which included creating a healthy state economy. During his term, Tyler met all the states expense needs and actually left the state's treasury with a $800,000 surplus upon leaving office. Other highlights of his term included the creation of a State Board of Fisheries to monitor the oyster and fish industry, the resolving of the Virginia-Tennessee boarder dispute, and the creation of a conditional pardon system. Tyler left office 1 January 1902 and returned to his home in Pulaski County. He died 3 January 1925.
Scope and Content
James Hoge Tyler's Executive Papers primarily consist of incoming correspondence during his term as governor from 1 January 1898 until 1 January 1902. The correspondence in this collection relates to a variety of topics including the mapping of the Virginia and Tennessee boarder; settling of Virginia and Maryland border disputes; the State Board of Fisheries; oyster farming; commerce; extradition requests; state expenses; criminal proceedings; the Department of the Navy; and others. In addition to correspondence, there are resolutions from the Virginia Senate and House of Delegates; reports; pardons; receipts; account ledgers; vouchers; newspaper articles; proclamations; deeds; resolutions to congress; petitions; and other sundry items.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Correspondence, 1898-1901
Series II. Excecutive Papers, 1860-1901
Each series is arranged in chronological order.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Gay, Jr., Thomas Edward, "The Life and Political Career of J. Hoge Tyler, Governor of Virginia, 1898-1902"(PhD dissertation, University of Virginia, 1969), 1-270.
Contents List
- Correspondence, 1898-1901., Extent: 5 Folders. (Box 1.)
  One of the key issues that Governor James Hoge Tyler worked to resolve when he entered office on January 1, 1898, was the on going dispute between Maryland and Virginia over their state water boundaries. Records related to the Virginia-Maryland border resolution can be found in 1898 and 1899. Included are the following: a letter from the J.B. Baylor of the U.S. Coast and Geodetic Survey informing Governor Tyler of Maryland's desire to settle the dispute (1898 February 23); a letter from J.B. Baylor detailing the Maryland state legislature's report on the Virginia-Maryland boundary (1898 March 1); a letter from J.B. Baylor discussing his work on creating an agreeable boundary line between Maryland and Virginia (1898 March 10); a joint report from survey engineers on the Virginia-Maryland boundary signed by J.B. Baylor and W.C. Hodgkins (1898); a letter from B.J. Hunter, Jr., discussing how to permanently mark the boundary between Virginia and Maryland and its estimated cost of $500 (1898); a report on the "Re-locating and Re-marking of the Boundary line between Maryland and Virginia in Tangier and Pocomoke Sounds" by T. Hodson and B. Gunter which includes a map (1898); a letter and final expense report on the Virginia-Maryland boundary issue from B. Gunter (1899 January 23); and a letter from B. Gunter requesting payment for his services (1899 January 28).
  Another important concern that Governor Tyler worked to resolve during his term was the surveying and mapping of the Virginia and Tennessee border. Records related to this issue are found in 1900 and 1901. Included are the following: a letter from J.B. Baylor estimating the total cost and recommending Congressional support (1900 April 16); a letter from J.B. Baylor detailing his work on gaining support from Congress to map the Virginia-Tennessee border (1900 April 28); letters and copies related to the Supreme Court case "State of Tennessee v. State of Virginia" from J.B. Baylor (1900 May 3); a letter from J.B. Baylor discussing the financial arrangements of surveying the Virginia-Tennessee border (1900 July 16); a letter to J.B. Baylor from A. H. Buchanan letting him know that the Tennessee legislature approved funding for the survey (1901 January 10); a letter from J.B. Baylor discussing the Supreme Court decisions that all cost of the mapping be split evenly between the two states (1901 May 17); financial reports and receipts from J.B. Baylor for his surveying and mapping work (1901 May, June, July, August, September, and October); and a letter from J.B. Baylor informing Governor Tyler that work is ending mapping the Virginia-Tennessee boarder (1901 November 1).
  Other topics that are discussed in Governor Tyler's correspondence include letters focusing on Virginia's commerce especially related to fishing and oysters. This includes a letter from J.B. Baylor asking Governor Tyler to take an active role in oyster legislation during his term (1898 February 25); and a letter from Seth F. Miller, Secretary of the State Board of Fisheries discussing the catching and pricing of oysters in King George County (1901 December 30). Correspondence about prisoner extraditions and court proceedings (1898 June 27) and about weapon ordinances with the Department of the Navy (1901 August 24) are also included.
  - Letters Received, 1898. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters Received, 1899. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters Received, 1900. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters Received, 1901 January - June. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters Received, 1901 July - December. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Executive Papers, 1860-1901., Extent: 6 Folders. (Box 1.)
  The Executive Papers of Governor Tyler include a variety of materials and encompass several different subjects. One of the larger topics covered relates to criminal proceedings such as pardons, commutations and extraditions. Some of the more interesting pardons granted by Governor Tyler include that of Edward Dabney who was sentenced to two years for seduction (1898); John Jackson, whose first degree murder charge a was commuted from hanging to life in prison (1898); and Charles Butler who was released from prison on the condition that he abstain from alcohol (1898). Other documents include correspondence from attorneys asking for the extradition of prisoners to and from Virginia. This includes letters from the Commonwealth's Attorney, Thomas Moore, asking Governor Tyler to request the extradition of two prisoners from West Virginia (1898 April 6), and a letter from J. E. Thrift asking for the extradition of a prisoner from Pennsylvania (1898 June 17).
  Other topics covered include letters of endorsement for B. L. Farinholt for the position of Chairman of the Board of Fisheries by the Senate of Virginia, Virginia House of Delegates, Henry Williams, and Dr. F.W. Lewis (1896).
  Also included are financial ledgers related to the Southwestern State Hospital. These reports are itemized records of the various types of expenditures including those for wages, drugs, groceries, telegrams, and advertising (1897-1901). There is also a list of the type and numbers of patients admitted by Superintendent R. J. Preston (1898 March 31).
  The Executive Papers of Governor Tyler also include a unique collection of documents including: a deed for the purchase of the James River and Kanawa Company (1860 May 9); a resolution from the General Assembly for the relinquishment of lands to the United States for the construction of life saving stations (1878 December 20); a newspaper article on the establishment of the Virginia Board of Fisheries; a resolution from the State of North Dakota to the United States Congress asking for the direct election of senators by the people; and a letter and petition to Governor Tyler from oyster packers and planters in Norfolk asking him to help enforce current Virginia laws on oyster farming.
  Finally, the Executive Papers of Governor Tyler include a Thanksgiving Day Proclamation which includes a reference to the recent assassination of President William McKinley (1901 November 28).
  - Miscellaneous, 1860-1894; undated. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - B. L. Farinholt; Endorsements for Chairman of Board of Fisheries, 1896; undated. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Financial Reports, Southwestern State Hospital, 1887-1901. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Pardons and Commutation Granted, 1898. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Requests for Extradition, 1898-1899. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Thanksgiving Day Proclamation, 1901 November 28. (Box 1, Folder 11)